[Music]
thanks and part to the American Heart
association's recommendation that
individuals at high risk for heart
disease ask their Physicians about
omega-3 fish oil supplementation fish
oil pills have grown into a
multi-billion doll industry We Now
consume more than 100,000 tons of fish
oil every year but what does the science
say are there purported benefits of fish
oil supplementation for the prevention
and treatment of heart disease promising
or just a
fishtail the scientific sea change
occurred a little over a decade ago when
a systematic review and metaanalysis
published in the Journal of the American
Medical Association looked at all the
best randomized clinical trials
evaluating the effects of omega-3 fats
on lifespan cardiac death sudden death
heart attack and stroke these included
studies not only on fish oil supplements
but also studies on the effects of
advising people to eat more oily fish
overall the researchers found no
protective benefit for overall mortality
heart disease mortality sudden cardiac
death heart attack or
stroke what about for someone who would
already had a heart attack and trying to
prevent another one still no benefit was
found since then another five dozen
randomized control trials have been
compiled and the most extensive
systematic assessment confirmed that
increas in the intake of fish fats EPA
and DHA had little or no effect on
deaths and cardiovascular events
longevity experiments on Mice found no
benefits for aging or lifespan either
where did we even get this idea that the
omega-3 fats and fish and fish oil
supplements were good for us there was a
notion that Eskimos were protected from
heart disease but that appears to be a
complete myth some early studies however
looked promising for example the famous
Dart trial from the 1980s involving
2,000 men found that those advised to
eat fatty fish had a 29% reduction in
mortality that's impressive no wonder
the study got a lot of attention fish
oil became a whale of a story that got
bigger with every telling but people
seem to have forgotten about the sequel
the dart 2 trial which found the exact
opposite run by the same group of
researchers the dart 2 trial wasn't even
bigger study 3,000 men but this time
participants advised to eat oily fish
and particularly those who were supplied
with fish oil capsules had a higher risk
of cardiac death concerns about the
potential proar rhythmic irregular
Rhythm inducing effects of fish oil has
led to reviews containing titles like
can fish oil kill you but again little
or no change in overall mortality risk
has been found when all the studies are
put
together Beyond just concerns about
persistent pollutants such as dioxins
and pcbs and fish oil supplements even
in distilled fish oil
supplements oxidation byproducts have
been found throughout the commercial
fish oil supplements industry surveys of
popular Omega-3 supplements in Asia
Europe the Middle East
Australia and North America found that
24 to 92% exceeded the voluntary safety
standards set by the industry there's no
legal limit at least in the United
States the country of origin didn't seem
to matter perhaps because most fish oil
products sold globally are evidently
sourced from the same region off the
west coast of South America surprisingly
the best before date also wasn't helpful
in this study where nine out of 10
supplements exceeded safety standards
they were all tested at least 9 months
before the best before dates the more
expensive ones were more contaminated
but this is thought to be an artifact of
higher cost relating to higher
concentrations those obtained from algae
were also better than those from
fish the United States has the highest
sales of fish oil in the world exceeding
a billion dollars a year when three top
selling fish oil supplements in the US
were tested they all exceeded the
recommended maximum levels of oxidation
products though expanded testing to four
dozen us supplements only found 52%
exceeded the limits and these two tests
may give false positives due to added
colors or flavors a USDA study found
that more than 70% contain less EPA and
or DHA than stated on their labels but
the greater concern is not what fish o
sment are lacking but rather what's not
listed on the label like the
contaminants oxidation byproducts and
saturated fat which may explain why fish
based Omega-3s raise LDL cholesterol
levels compared to plant-based
Omega-3s the public health implications
of consuming oxidized fish oil are
unclear however animal experiments
suggest chronic exposure can cause
inflammation organ toxicity and
accelerated
atherosclerosis but no long-term human
Studies have been done ironically one of
the reasons there haven't been more
clinical studies are the ethical
concerns knowingly exposing people to
oxidize fats yet that experiment is
being carried out on mass as we speak in
bathroom medicine cabinets suround the
world after putting all the studies
together the authors of the landmark AMA
Journal metaanalysis concluded that
there was no longer justification for
the use of Omega-3s in everyday clinical
practice what should doctors do when
their patients follow the American Heart
association's advice and inquire about
fish supplements well that's the
director of lipids and Metabolism at
Mount Sinai cardiovascular Institute put
it given this another negative meta
analysis our job as doctors should be to
stop highly marketed fish o
supplementation to all our
patients the research momentum was
already in full swing though and five
massive new trials have been recently
published randomizing tens of thousands
to various formulations of fish oil
versus placebo four out of five flopped
the so-called Ascend trial the Omi trial
strength trial and the vital trial all
failed to reduce deaths or
cardiovascular events but one final nail
in the cofin appeared to be loose the
reduce it trial didn't significantly
reduce overall mortality but did reduce
a compositive cardiovascular events by
25% it used a prescription only dose of
EPA equivalent to eating about 150 cans
of tuna fish a day the problem is the
placebo they used on likee other trials
that used more neutral oils like corn
oil the drug company that funded reduce
it to promote its own product chose
mineral oil for the control group a
classic drug industry trick where you
try to make your product look better by
comparing it against something worse and
indeed the mineral oil quote unquote
Placebo increased LDL cholesterol and
caused more than 30% increase in C
reactive protein no wonder the fish oil
looked good in comparison it's possible
some fish oil formulation will
eventually prove to be helpful but for
now metaanalyses unequivocally
demonstrate that there is no
cardiovascular benefit to
over-the-counter fish oil
[Music]
supplements